Liang Guo Espland, PhD

Monterey, CA liangespland@gmail.com Cell: 952-465-1093 https://www.linkedin.com/in/liang-guo-espland/ Motivated software engineer with experience in programming, software design and development, web application, APIs, and databases. A problem-solver with growth mindset. Great organizing and time management skills. Excellent written and verbal communication skills.

Skills

Programming: Python, Java, Javascript, HTML, CSS, SQL, R

Tools: Django, Flask, Node.js, Git, Docker, Postman, JQuery, Heroku, bash, JSON, cloud service (e.g. AWS)

Databases: Relational databases (e.g. SQLite, PostgreSQL), nonSQL databases (e.g. MongoDB)

Projects

A Personal Portfolio website (https://happycoding47.pythonanywhere.com/)

- Built a responsive portfolio website with Python, HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap 4 and Django
- Published the website on PythonAnywhere

A To-do List Manager web application (https://espland-to-do-list.herokuapp.com/)

- Used Django to create a website where a user can sign up for an account and fully manage a to-do list.
- Established an user authentication system (sign up, login, logout)
- Created a CRUD application (Create, Read, Update, Delete)
- Tested the application with Pytest before deployed to Heroku

A resource-based, production-ready REST API (https://rest-apis-flask.onrender.com/swagger-ui)

- Created a REST API that includes authentication, deployments, and databases with Python, Flask and SQL
- Containerized the application using Docker
- Used SQLAlchemy to store resources to a SQLite database or a PostgreSQL database (for production)
- Hosted the API to Render and tested with Postman (endpoint: https://rest-apis-flask.onrender.com)

Education and Scholarships

University of Washington, Seattle, WA - Software Development & Design Essentials Certificate Program 2021

My Career Advancement Account Scholarship, Department of Defense, US gov

Operation Jump Start Scholarship, Monterey Bay Military Spouse Club

University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN - **Ph. D.** in Molecular Biology **(GPA 3.8/4.0)** 2012 – 2018

• Institute for Molecular Virology Fellowship, National Institute of Health, three consecutive years

China Agricultural University, Beijing, China - B.S. (GPA 3.8/4.0)

• National Scholarship (Top 1%), China gov, three consecutive years

2006 - 2011

Professional and Community Experience

Self-learning programming enthusiast

2019 - present

- Obtained certificates for online courses, such as The Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs, Full Stack Websites with Python Web Development, The complete Node is Developer Course, Advanced Python Programming: build 10 Object Oriented Programming (OOP) Applications, etc.
- Oracle Certified Associate, Java SE8 Programmer
- Contribute to Open Source Communities such as Github and Gitlab, e.g. participated in Hacktoberfest 2022

Member of MilSpouse Coders.

2020 - present

• Design and develop projects individually and as a team member; Debugging and testing; Provide code reviews
The Economic Development Fellows Consulting Program, University of Minnesota 2018

Used Python and Selenium to scrape and process information from websites that contain labor statistics

Employment History

Patient Care Technician - Avera McKennan Hospital, Sioux Falls, SD

2019 - 2020

 Demonstrated time management and organizing skills in a fast-paced workplace; Worked independently as well as collaboratively within cross-functional teams; Mentored junior trainees; Communicated effectively with customers and increased their satisfaction

Research Assistant - University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN

2012 - 2018

• Developed an application using Python and R to help analyze high throughput genetic sequencing data generated from biomedical experiments, which led to a publication in a top journal (Nucleic Acids Research, Impact Factor 19.16)